I've been thinking a lot about the world recently
لقد كنت أفكر بالعالم كثيرًا هذه الأيام
and how it's changed over the last 20, 30, 40 years.
وكيف تغير في ال20 و30 و40 سنة الماضية.
Twenty or 30 years ago,
منذ عشرين أو ثلاثين سنة،
if a chicken caught a cold and sneezed and died
إذا أصيبت دجاجة بالبرد وعطست ثم ماتت
in a remote village in East Asia,
بقرية معزولة في شرق آسيا،
it would have been a tragedy for the chicken
ستكون مأساة بالنسبة للدجاجة،
and its closest relatives,
وأقربائها،
but I don't think there was much possibility
ولكن لا أعتقد أنه كان يوجد احتمال
of us fearing a global pandemic
بأننا سنخاف بسببها من وباء عالمي
and the deaths of millions.
وموت الملايين.
Twenty or 30 years ago, if a bank in North America
منذ 20 أو 30 سنة مضت، لو أن بنكا في شمال أمريكا
lent too much money to some people
أقرض أموالا كثيرة لبعض الأشخاص
who couldn't afford to pay it back
الذين لا يقدرون على ردها
and the bank went bust,
وأفلس ذلك البنك،
that was bad for the lender
لأصبح من سوء حظ المقرض
and bad for the borrower,
والمقترض،
but we didn't imagine it would bring
ولكننا لم نكن نتخيل أنه سيجعل
the global economic system to its knees
الاقتصاد العالمي ينحني على ركبتيه
for nearly a decade.
على امتداد قرن تقريبًا.
This is globalization.
هذه هي العولمة.
This is the miracle that has enabled us
هذه هي المعجزة التي أمكنتنا
to transship our bodies and our minds
من نقل أبداننا وعقولنا
and our words and our pictures and our ideas
وكلماتنا وصورنا وأفكارنا
and our teaching and our learning around the planet
وتعليمنا وما تعلمناه حول الكرة الأرضية
ever faster and ever cheaper.
بشكل أسرع وأرخص.
It's brought a lot of bad stuff,
لقد جلبت العولمة العديد من المساوئ،
like the stuff that I just described,
مثل الأشياء التي ذكرتها منذ قليل،
but it's also brought a lot of good stuff.
ولكنها جلبت العديد من الخيرات أيضًا.
A lot of us are not aware
الكثير مننا غير واعون بها
of the extraordinary successes of the Millennium Development Goals,
كالنجاحات الباهرة لللأهداف الإنمائية للألفية التابعة للأمم المتحدة،
several of which have achieved their targets
العديد منها وصلت لأهدافها
long before the due date.
قبل موعدها النهائي.
That proves that this species of humanity
هذا يثبت أن هذه الفصائل من البشر
is capable of achieving extraordinary progress
قادرة على تحقيق تقدم باهر وجبار
if it really acts together and it really tries hard.
إن تعاوانوا مع بعضهم البعض وحاولوا بكل مقدرتهم.
But if I had to put it in a nutshell these days,
ولكن إذا كان علي أن أبسط أكثر،
I sort of feel that globalization
أشعر نوعًا ما بأن العولمة
has taken us by surprise,
قد فاجأتنا،
and we've been slow to respond to it.
فكان ردنا عليها بطيئًا جدًا.
If you look at the downside of globalization,
إذا نظرت إلى الجانب السلبي للعولمة،
it really does seem to be sometimes overwhelming.
يبدو أحيانًا بأنه كثير للغاية.
All of the grand challenges that we face today,
كل التحديات الكبيرة التي نواجهها اليوم،
like climate change and human rights
مثل التغيرات المناخية وحقوق الإنسان
and demographics and terrorism and pandemics
والعدد السكاني والإرهاب والأوبئة
and narco-trafficking and human slavery
والإتجار بالمخدرات وبالعبيد
and species loss, I could go on,
وانقراض بعض الكائنات، لا نهاية لهذا الحديث...
we're not making an awful lot of progress
يبدو أننا لا نتقدم بشكل كبير
against an awful lot of those challenges.
ضد هذه التحديات الصعبة.
So in a nutshell, that's the challenge
الزبدة أنه هذا هو التحدي
that we all face today
الذي نواجهه جميعنا اليوم
at this interesting point in history.
في هذه اللحظة المثيرة للاهتمام بالتاريخ.
That's clearly what we've got to do next.
هذا ما علينا فعله لاحقا.
We've somehow got to get our act together
يجب علينا بطريقة ما أن نتامالك أنفسنا ونوحد طريقة عملنا
and we've got to figure out how to globalize
ويجب علينا أن نكتشف كيف نعولم
the solutions better
الحلول بشكل أفضل
so that we don't simply become a species
بحيث أن لا نكون الفصيلة
which is the victim of the globalization of problems.
التي تصبح ضحية لمشاكل العولمة
Why are we so slow at achieving these advances?
لماذا نحن بطيئون في تحقيق التقدم؟
What's the reason for it?
ما هو السبب؟
Well, there are, of course, a number of reasons,
بالطبع، هنالك العديد من الأسباب،
but perhaps the primary reason
ولكن لعل السبب الرئيسي هو
is because we're still organized as a species
أننا ما زلنا منظمين كفصيلة
in the same way that we were organized
تمامًا كما كنا
200 or 300 years ago.
قبل مئتين أو ثلاثمئة سنة مضت.
There's one superpower left on the planet
هنالك قوة خارقة وحيدة باقية على هذا الكوكب
and that is the seven billion people,
وتلك القوة هي السبعة مليارات إنسان،
the seven billion of us who cause all these problems,
السبعة مليارات منّا هم من سببوا تلك المشاكل،
the same seven billion, by the way,
ونفسهم، بالمناسبة،
who will resolve them all.
هم من يشكلون حلها جميعها.
But how are those seven billion organized?
ولكن كيف يمكن تنظيم هذه السبع مليارات؟
They're still organized in 200 or so nation-states,
مازالوا منظمين بشكل مئتي أمة أو أكثر،
and the nations have governments
وهذه الأمم لديها من يحكمها
that make rules
ويحدد القوانين
and cause us to behave in certain ways.
وذلك يدفعنا إلى التصرف بطرق معينة.
And that's a pretty efficient system,
وهذا في الحقيقة نظام فعّال جدًا،
but the problem is that the way that those laws are made
ولكن تكمن المشكلة بالطريقة التي نشأت بها تلك القوانين
and the way those governments think
وطريقة تفكير الحكومة نفسها
is absolutely wrong for the solution of global problems,
خاطئة لحل المشاكل العالمية،
because it all looks inwards.
لأنها تهم جميعها بالداخل.
The politicians that we elect
السياسيون الذين ننتخبهم
and the politicians we don't elect, on the whole,
والذين لا ننتخبهم، بشكل عام،
have minds that microscope.
لديهم عقول مايكروسكوب.
They don't have minds that telescope.
وليست لديهم عقول تيليسكوب.
They look in. They pretend, they behave,
ينظرون للداخل. يتظاهرون ويتصرفون،
as if they believed that every country was an island
كأن بلادهم هي جزيرة معزولة
that existed quite happily, independently
نشأت باستقلالية وبسعادة
of all the others
من دون الآخرين
on its own little planet
في كوكبها الخاص
in its own little solar system.
في مجالها الفضائي الخاص.
This is the problem:
هذه هي المشكلة:
countries competing against each other,
تتنافس بعض البلاد ضد بعضها،
countries fighting against each other.
ويقاتلون بعضهم البعض.
This week, as any week you care to look at,
هذا الأسبوع، كأي أسبوع سترى،
you'll find people actually trying to kill each other from country to country,
ستجد أشخاصا يحاولون قتل بعضهم من بلد لآخر،
but even when that's not going on,
وحتى عندما لا يحدث ذلك،
there's competition between countries,
تبقى المنافسة بين الدول،
each one trying to shaft the next.
كل دولة تحاول أن تطلق الرمح على الأخرى.
This is clearly not a good arrangement.
هذا بكل وضوح اتفاق غير جيد.
We clearly need to change it.
واضح أنه يجب علينا تغييره.
We clearly need to find ways
يجب علينا أن نجد حلولا
of encouraging countries to start working together
لتشجيع العمل التعاوني بين الدول
a little bit better.
بشكل أفضل.
And why won't they do that?
ولماذا لا يبادرون بذلك؟
Why is it that our leaders still persist in looking inwards?
لماذا يصّر قادتنا على حد النظر إلى الداخل؟
Well, the first and most obvious reason
حسنًا، أول سبب وأكثرها وضوحًا...
is because that's what we ask them to do.
هو لأنه هذا ما نطلبه منهم.
That's what we tell them to do.
هذا ما نقول لهم أن يفعلوه.
When we elect governments
عندما ننتخبهم
or when we tolerate unelected governments,
أو عندما نتحمل الحكومات الغير منتخبة،
we're effectively telling them that what we want
نحن نقول لهم وبشكل واضح ما نريده
is for them to deliver us in our country
نريد منهم أن "يخلصونا" داخل بلادنا
a certain number of things.
هنالك العديد من الأمور.
We want them to deliver prosperity,
نريد منهم أن يوصلونا إلى الازدهار،
growth, competitiveness, transparency, justice
والنمو والتنافس والشفافية والعدالة
and all of those things.
وكل تلك المتطلبات.
So unless we start asking our governments
لذا، إن لم نبدأ بمطالبتهم
to think outside a little bit,
بالتفكير في الخارج قليلًا،
to consider the global problems that will finish us all
ليفكروا بالمشاكل العالمية التي ستنهينا جميعًا
if we don't start considering them,
إذا لم نبدأ في النظر إليها،
then we can hardly blame them
عندها، لا يسعنا أن نلوم حكومتنا أبدًا
if what they carry on doing is looking inwards,
إذا استمروا بالنظر إلى الداخل،
if they still have minds that microscope
إذا ما زال لديهم عقول كالمايكروسكوب
rather than minds that telescope.
عوضًا عن عقول كالتيليسكوب.
That's the first reason why things tend not to change.
هذا هوا السبب الأول لعدم قدرتنا على التغيير.
The second reason is that these governments,
السبب الثاني هو أنه هذه الحكومات،
just like all the rest of us,
مثلنا جميعًا،
are cultural psychopaths.
مريضة عقليا ثقافيًا.
I don't mean to be rude,
لا أقصد أن أكون فظًا،
but you know what a psychopath is.
ولكن تعلمون ما هو المريض النفسي.
A psychopath is a person who,
المريض النفسي هو شخص،
unfortunately for him or her,
لسوء حظه،
lacks the ability to really empathize
لا يملك القدرة على التعاطف
with other human beings.
مع البشر الآخرين.
When they look around,
عندما ينظرون حولهم،
they don't see other human beings
لا يرون بشرا آخرين
with deep, rich, three-dimensional personal lives
بحياة شخصية غنية وعميقة وثلاثية الأبعاد
and aims and ambitions.
مع أهداف وأحلام.
What they see is cardboard cutouts,
كل ما يرونه هو لوح كرتوني،
and it's very sad and it's very lonely,
وذلك مثير للشفقة، والوحدة،
and it's very rare, fortunately.
ولحسن الحظ إنه من النادر جدًا.
But actually, aren't most of us
ولكن في الحقيقة، أليس معظمنا
not really so very good at empathy?
غير قادرين على التقمص العاطفي؟
Oh sure, we're very good at empathy
بالتأكيد نحن قادرون على ذلك
when it's a question of dealing with people
عندما يتعلق الأمر بالتعامل مع أشخاص
who kind of look like us
يشبهوننا نوعا ما
and kind of walk and talk and eat and pray
يمشون مثلنا ويتكلمون ويأكلون ويصلون
and wear like us,
ويلبسون مثلنا،
but when it comes to people who don't do that,
ولكن عندما يتعلق الأمر بالأشخاص المختلفين عنا،
who don't quite dress like us
الذين لا يرتدون مثل ثيابنا
and don't quite pray like us
ولا يصلون مثلنا
and don't quite talk like us,
ولا يتكلمون مثلنا،
do we not also have a tendency to see them
ألا نميل عندها ولو قليلًا
ever so slightly as cardboard cutouts too?
لأن نراهم كألواح كرتونية أيضًا؟
And this is a question we need to ask ourselves.
وهذا السؤال علينا أن نطرحه على أنفسنا.
I think constantly we have to monitor it.
أعتقد أنه علينا مراقبته دومًا.
Are we and our politicians to a degree
هل نتفق نحن والسياسون إلى حد ما
cultural psychopaths?
على المرض النفسي الثقافي؟
The third reason is hardly worth mentioning
السبب الثالث غير جدير بالذكر
because it's so silly,
لأنه سخيف جدًا،
but there's a belief amongst governments
ولكن هنالك إيمان منتشر في حكومتنا
that the domestic agenda
أن المخططات المحلية
and the international agenda
والمخططات العالمية
are incompatible and always will be.
متعارضة دائمًا وستبقى كذلك.
This is just nonsense.
هذا مجرد هراء.
In my day job, I'm a policy adviser.
في عملي اليومي، أنا مستشار سياسي.
I've spent the last 15 years or so
قضيت ما يقارب ال 15 سنة الأخيرة
advising governments around the world,
مقدمًا النصائح للحكومات حول العالم،
and in all of that time I have never once seen
وخلال كل هذه المدة لم أر أبدًا
a single domestic policy issue
مشكلة واحدة محلية
that could not be more imaginatively,
لم يمكن حلها بشكل خيالي،
effectively and rapidly resolved
وفعًالي وسريع
than by treating it as an international problem,
عندما نتعامل معها كمشكلة عالمية،
looking at the international context,
عندما ننظر بالمنظور العالمي،
comparing what others have done,
نقارن كيف تعاملت بعض الدول مع هذه المشكلة،
bringing in others, working externally
نجلب الآخرين معًأ ونعمل خارجيًا
instead of working internally.
عوضًا عن العمل داخليًا.
And so you may say, well, given all of that,
ولذا، يمكنك القول بناء على كل ذلك،
why then doesn't it work?
لماذا إذا لا تنجح؟
Why can we not make our politicians change?
لماذا لا نستطيع تغيير السياسين؟
Why can't we demand them?
لماذا لا نطالبهم بذلك؟
Well I, like a lot of us, spend a lot of time complaining
حسنا، أنا مثل الآخرين منا الذين يقضون وقتهم بالتذمر
about how hard it is to make people change,
كيف أنه من الصعب تغيير الآخرين،
and I don't think we should fuss about it.
ولا أعتقد أنه علينا خلق مشكلة كبيرة من ذلك.
I think we should just accept
أعتقد أنه علينا أن نتقبل
that we are an inherently conservative species.
أننا بالفطرة كائنات محافظة.
We don't like to change.
لا نحب أن نتغير.
It exists for very sensible evolutionary reasons.
وجد هذا لكي يحافظ على بقائنا.
We probably wouldn't still be here today
لم نكن لنوجد اليوم هنا
if we weren't so resistant to change.
لو لم نكن مقاومين للتغيير.
It's very simple: Many thousands of years ago,
الأمر بسيط للغاية: منذ آلاف السنين
we discovered that if we carried on
اكتشفنا أنه إذا استمريّنا
doing the same things, we wouldn't die,
بتكرار ما نفعله، فلن نموت،
because the things that we've done before
لأن ما قمنا بفعله في المرات السابقة
by definition didn't kill us,
لم يقتلنا،
and therefore as long as we carry on doing them,
لذا، إذا استمرينا بفعله،
we'll be okay,
فسنكون بخير،
and it's very sensible not to do anything new,
وكان من المنطق ألا نفعل أي شيء جديد،
because it might kill you.
لأنه من المتوقع أن يقتلنا.
But of course, there are exceptions to that.
ولكن بالتأكيد هنالك استثناء لذلك.
Otherwise, we'd never get anywhere.
وإلا لما كنا تقدمنا.
And one of the exceptions, the interesting exception,
ومن تلك الاستثنائات المثيرة للاهتمام،
is when you can show to people
هو عندما تستطيع أن تظهر للناس
that there might be some self-interest
أنه من الممكن أن توجد مصلحة خاصة
in them making that leap of faith
في قفزهم نحو المجهول
and changing a little bit.
والتغير ولو قليلا.
So I've spent a lot of the last 10 or 15 years
لذا قضيت الكثير من ال10 أو 15 سنة الماضية
trying to find out what could be that self-interest
محاولًا أن أجد ما هي تلك المصلحة الخاصة
that would encourage not just politicians
التي ستشجع ليس السياسين فقط
but also businesses and general populations,
بل رجال الأعمال والجميع،
all of us, to start to think a little more outwardly,
جميعنا، ونبدأ في التفكير خارجيًا بالتدرج،
to think in a bigger picture,
نفكر بالصورة الكبيرة،
not always to look inwards, sometimes to look outwards.
لا لننظر إلى الداخل دائما، ولكن لننظر إلى الخارج أحيانًا.
And this is where I discovered
وهذا ما اكتشفته
something quite important.
شيء مهم جدا.
In 2005, I launched a study
سنة 2005، بدأت دراسة
called the Nation Brands Index.
تسمى بمؤشر العلامة التجارية للبلد.
What it is, it's a very large-scale study that polls
ما يعني، أنها دراسة على مستوى كبير
a very large sample of the world's population,
تشمل عينة كبيرة من سكان العالم،
a sample that represents about 70 percent
عينة تمثّل حوالي 70%
of the planet's population,
من سكان العالم تقريبًا،
and I started asking them a series of questions
وبدأت بطرح الأسئلة عليهم
about how they perceive other countries.
عن رؤيتهم للبلدان الأخرى.
And the Nation Brands Index over the years
ومؤشر العلامة التجارية للبلد على امتداد السنوات
has grown to be a very, very large database.
ازداد حجمًا وأصبح قاعدة بيانات كبيرة جدًا.
It's about 200 billion data points
بحاولي 200 مليار نقاط بيانية
tracking what ordinary people think about other countries
مستهدفًا رؤية عامة الناس للبلدان المختلفة
and why.
ولماذا ذلك.
Why did I do this? Well, because the governments that I advise
لماذا قمت بذلك؟ حسنا، لأن الحكومات التي قمت بإرشادها
are very, very keen on knowing
كانت مهتمة جدًا بمعرفة
how they are regarded.
كيف يراها الآخرون.
They've known, partly because
لقد اهتموا بذلك لأني
I've encouraged them to realize it,
شجعتهم ليدركوا ذلك،
that countries depend
أن الدول تعتمد
enormously on their reputations
بشكل كبير على سمعتها
in order to survive and prosper in the world.
لكي تنجح وتنجو في العالم.
If a country has a great, positive image,
إذا كانت الدولة تمتلك صورة إيجابية عظيمة،
like Germany has or Sweden or Switzerland,
مثل ألمانيا أو السويد أو سويسرا،
everything is easy and everything is cheap.
كل شيء سيكون سهلا ورخيصا.
You get more tourists. You get more investors.
تحصل على مزيد من السياح والمستثمرين.
You sell your products more expensively.
تبيع منجاتك بسعر عالي
If, on the other hand, you have a country
من الناحية الآخرى، إذا كانت الدولة
with a very weak or a very negative image,
تملك صورة ضعيفة أو سلبية،
everything is difficult and everything is expensive.
كل شيء سيكون صعبا ومكلفا.
So governments care desperately
لذا تهتم الحكومات بشكل كبير
about the image of their country,
بصورة دولتهم،
because it makes a direct difference
لأنها تؤثر مباشرة
to how much money they can make,
على مقدار المال الذي سيجنونه،
and that's what they've promised their populations
وهو ما وعدوا شعوبهم
they're going to deliver.
بأنهم سيقدمونه.
So a couple of years ago, I thought I would take
إذا، منذ بضع سنين، فكرت أخذ
some time out and speak to that gigantic database
إجازة والتوجه لقاعدة البيانات تلك
and ask it,
وسؤالها،
why do some people prefer one country
لماذا يفضل الناس بعض الدول
more than another?
أكثر من الأخرى؟
And the answer that the database gave me
والإجابة التي حصلت عليها من قاعدة البيانات
completely staggered me.
صدمتني للغاية.
It was 6.8.
كانت 6.8.
I haven't got time to explain in detail.
لا أملك الوقت الكافي لأشرح بالتفصيل.
Basically what it told me was —
بشكل عام ما أظهرته هو،
(Laughter) (Applause) —
(ضحك) (تصفيق)،
the kinds of countries we prefer are good countries.
الدول التي نفضلها هيا الدول الخَيّرة.
We don't admire countries primarily because they're rich,
لا نعجب بالدول لأنها غنية،
because they're powerful, because they're successful,
ولا لأنها قوية أو لأنها ناجحة،
because they're modern, because they're technologically advanced.
أو لأنها عصرية، أو لأنها متقدمة تكنولوجيًا.
We primarily admire countries that are good.
نعجب الدول الخَيّرة بشكل أساسي.
What do we mean by good?
ولكن ماذا نعني بخَيّرة؟
We mean countries that seem to contribute
نقصد بذلك الدولة التي تساهم
something to the world in which we live,
بطريقة ما في عالمنا الذي نعيش فيه،
countries that actually make the world safer
الدول التي تجعل العالم أكثر أمنًا
or better or richer or fairer.
أو أفضل أو أغنى أو أكثر عدلًا.
Those are the countries we like.
تلك هي الدولة التي نحبها.
This is a discovery of significant importance —
هذا الاكتشاف مهم جدًا،
you see where I'm going —
نعم، هل ترى ما أقصده؟،
because it squares the circle.
لأنه يحدد الدائرة.
I can now say, and often do, to any government,
أستطيع أن أقول الآن، وغالبًا ما أقوله للحكومات،
in order to do well, you need to do good.
لكي تتقدم عليك أن تفعل الخير.
If you want to sell more products,
إذا أردت بيع منتجات أكثر،
if you want to get more investment,
أو تستثمر أكثر،
if you want to become more competitive,
إذا أردت أن تكون قادرًا على التنافس،
then you need to start behaving,
إذا عليك أن تحسن طريقة تصرفك،
because that's why people will respect you
لأن ذلك ما سيجعل الناس يحترمونك
and do business with you,
ويتعاملون معك تجاريًا،
and therefore, the more you collaborate,
وهكذا، كلما تعاونت مع الغير،
the more competitive you become.
كلما أصبحت أكثر قدرة على التنافس.
This is quite an important discovery,
هذا اكتشاف عظيم ومهم،
and as soon as I discovered this,
وبمجرد ما اكتشفته،
I felt another index coming on.
شعرت باقتراب مؤشر آخر.
I swear that as I get older, my ideas become simpler
أقسم أنه كلما تقدمت في العمر، كلما أصبحت أفكاري أكثر بساطة
and more and more childish.
وأكثر طفولية.
This one is called the Good Country Index,
المؤشر الجديد إسمه "مؤشر الدول الخَيّرة"،
and it does exactly what it says on the tin.
ووظيفته من إسمه.
It measures, or at least it tries to measure,
يقيس، أو على الأقل، يحاول أن يقيس،
exactly how much each country on Earth contributes
ما تساهم به كل دولة بالتحديد في هذه الأرض
not to its own population but to the rest of humanity.
ليس لشعبها، ولكن للبشرية أجمع.
Bizarrely, nobody had ever thought
من الغريب أن أحدا لم يفكر
of measuring this before.
بقياسه من قبل.
So my colleague Dr. Robert Govers and I have spent
لذا قضيت أنا وزميلي د. روبيرت جوفيرس
the best part of the last two years,
معظم وقتنا في السنتين الأخيرتين،
with the help of a large number of very serious and clever people,
في مساعدة العديد من الأشخاص الأذكياء والجادين،
cramming together all the reliable data in the world
محاولين أن نحصر كل البيانات المعتمدة الموجودة في العالم
we could find about what countries give
لنعرف أي دولة تخدم وتعطي
to the world.
للعالم.
And you're waiting for me to tell you which one comes top.
ويبدو أنكم تنتظرون مني أن أعلن من حل في المركز الأول.
And I'm going to tell you,
وسأقوم بإخباركم،
but first of all I want to tell you
ولكن أريد أن أقول أولًا
precisely what I mean
ما أقصده بالتحديد
when I say a good country.
عندما أقول دولة خَيّرة.
I do not mean morally good.
لا أقصد خَيّرة أخلاقيًا.
When I say that Country X
عندما أقول الدولة x
is the goodest country on Earth,
هي الأكثر خيرية في الأرض،
and I mean goodest, I don't mean best.
وعندما أقول الأكثر خيرية لا أعني الأفضل.
Best is something different.
الأفضل شيء مختلف كليًا.
When you're talking about a good country,
عندما نتحدث عن بلاد خيّرة،
you can be good, gooder and goodest.
يمكنك أن تكون حسن أو أحسن أو الأحسن.
It's not the same thing as good, better and best.
هذا ليس نفس الشيء عندما نقول جيد أو أفضل أو الأفضل.
This is a country which simply gives more
هذه دولة بكل بساطة تعطي أكثر
to humanity than any other country.
للبشرية وللعالم أكثر من أي دولة أخرى.
I don't talk about how they behave at home
لا أتكلم عن طريقة تصرفها داخل بلادها
because that's measured elsewhere.
لأن ذلك مقاس في مكان آخر.
And the winner is
والفائز هو
Ireland.
أيرلندا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
According to the data here,
وفقًا للبيانات هنا،
no country on Earth, per head of population,
لا توجد دولة على الأرض، بمعدل السكان،
per dollar of GDP, contributes more
بمعدل الإنتاج المحلي الإجمالي لها، تساهم أكثر لعالمنا
to the world that we live in than Ireland.
أكثر من أيرلندا.
What does this mean?
ماذا يعني ذلك؟
This means that as we go to sleep at night,
هذا يعني أنه عندما نخلد إلى النوم ليلا،
all of us in the last 15 seconds before we drift off to sleep,
جميعنا في ال15 ثانية الأخيرة من النوم العميق،
our final thought should be,
آخر ما نفكر فيه يجب أن يكون،
godammit, I'm glad that Ireland exists.
يا إلهي، كم أنا ممتن لوجود أيرلندا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And that — (Applause) —
وهذا - (تصفيق) -
In the depths of a very severe economic recession,
في عمق كساد اقتصادي شديد،
I think that there's a really important lesson there,
أعتقد أنه هنالك درس مهم جدا،
that if you can remember your international obligations
أنه إذا تذكرت التزاماتك الدولية
whilst you are trying to rebuild your own economy,
وأنت تحاول إعادة بناء اقتصادك الداخلي،
that's really something.
فإن ذلك أمر مهم.
Finland ranks pretty much the same.
فينلندا تقارب الترتيب.
The only reason why it's below Ireland
السبب الوحيد لوجودها تحت إيرلندا
is because its lowest score is lower than Ireland's lowest score.
لأن أدنى علامة لها هي أدنى من أدنى علامة لإيرلندا.
Now the other thing you'll notice about the top 10 there
وما ستلاحظه في العشرة الأوائل
is, of course, they're all, apart from New Zealand,
معظمهم، باستثناء نيوزيلندا،
Western European nations.
دول من أوروبا الغربية.
They're also all rich.
وجميعها دول غنية أيضًا.
This depressed me,
وهذا يحبطني للغاية،
because one of the things that I did not want
لأنه من الأشياء التي لم أرد
to discover with this index
أن أكتشفها في البحث
is that it's purely the province of rich countries
أنه من دور وإختصاص الدول الغنية فقط
to help poor countries.
أن تساعد الدول الفقيرة.
This is not what it's all about.
هذا ليس كل ما في الأمر.
And indeed, if you look further down the list,
وبالنظر إلى أسفل القائمة،
I don't have the slide here, you will see
لا أملك الشريحة هنا، سترون
something that made me very happy indeed,
سترون شيئا ما جعلني سعيدا،
that Kenya is in the top 30,
أن كينيا موجودة بأعلى 30 دولة،
and that demonstrates one very, very important thing.
وهذا يمثل شيئا مهمًا جدًا.
This is not about money.
المال ليس كل شيء.
This is about attitude.
للأمر علاقة بالسلوك.
This is about culture.
وله علاقة بالثقافة.
This is about a government and a people that care
وله علاقة بالحكومات والأفراد الذين يهتمون
about the rest of the world
ببقية العالم
and have the imagination and the courage
ولديهم القدرة على التخيل والشجاعة
to think outwards instead of only thinking selfishly.
للتفكير بالخارج عوضًا عن التفكير بأنانية.
I'm going to whip through the other slides
سأقوم بتحريك الشرائح بسرعة
just so you can see some of the lower-lying countries.
لتستطيعوا أن تروا بعض الدول المتأخرة في الترتيب.
There's Germany at 13th, the U.S. comes 21st,
ألمانيا في المرتبة 13، والولايات المتحدة تأتي في المرتبة 21،
Mexico comes 66th,
المكسيك 66،
and then we have some of the big developing countries,
ولدينا بعض من الدول المتقدمة،
like Russia at 95th, China at 107th.
مثل روسيا في المرتبة 95، والصين في المرتبة 107.
Countries like China and Russia and India,
دول مثل الصين وروسيا والهند،
which is down in the same part of the index,
وهم من الدول في أسفل التصنيف،
well, in some ways, it's not surprising.
حسنًا، قد لا يبدو ذلك مفاجئًا.
They've spent a great deal of time
لقد أمضوا معظم وقتهم في الحقبة الماضية
over the last decades building their own economy,
في بناء اقتصادهم الخاص،
building their own society and their own polity,
بناء مجتمعاتهم وحكوماتهم،
but it is to be hoped
ولكن ما نتمناه
that the second phase of their growth
هو أنه في المرحلة الثانية من التنمية
will be somewhat more outward-looking
سينظرون إلى الخارج قليلًا
than the first phase has been so far.
أكثر مما فعلوا في مرحلتهم الأولى.
And then you can break down each country
وهكذا يمكنك أن تصنف كل دولة
in terms of the actual datasets that build into it.
بنائًا على مجموع البيانات.
I'll allow you to do that.
سأمكنكم من فعل ذلك.
From midnight tonight it's going to be on goodcountry.org,
ابتداءً من منتصف اللية، سيكون متوفرا في: goodcountry.org
and you can look at the country.
ويمكنك إلقاء نظرة على ترتيب الدول.
You can look right down to the level of the individual datasets.
يمكنكم رؤية البيانات الخاصة لكل دولة أيضًا.
Now that's the Good Country Index.
والآن، هذا هو مؤشر الدول الخيّرة.
What's it there for?
لماذا هو موجود؟
Well, it's there really because I want to try
حسنًا، هو موجود لأني أحاول
to introduce this word,
أن أقدم هذه الكلمة،
or reintroduce this word, into the discourse.
أو أعيد تقديم هذه الكلمة في الخطاب.
I've had enough hearing about competitive countries.
لقد اكتفيت من السماع عن الدول المتنافسة.
I've had enough hearing about
اكتفيت من السماع عن
prosperous, wealthy, fast-growing countries.
الدول الناجحة والغنية وسريعة النمو.
I've even had enough hearing about happy countries
لقد اكتفيت من السماع عن الدول السعيدة
because in the end that's still selfish.
لأنه في نهاية الأمر ما يزال فعلا أنانيا.
That's still about us,
ما زال الأمر يتعلق بنا شخصيا،
and if we carry on thinking about us,
وإذا استمرينا بالتفكير بأنفسنا،
we are in deep, deep trouble.
سنكون بمشكلة كبيرة.
I think we all know what it is
أعتقد أننا جميعًا نعرف ما
that we want to hear about.
نريد أن نسمع عنه&gt;
We want to hear about good countries,
نريد أن نسمع عن الدول الخيرة،
and so I want to ask you all a favor.
لذا، أريد أن أطلب منك خدمة.
I'm not asking a lot.
لا أطلب الكثير.
It's something that you might find easy to do
إنه أمر ستجدونه سهلا
and you might even find enjoyable
وربما تستمتعون به أيضًا
and even helpful to do,
ومفيدًا للقيام به حتى،
and that's simply to start using the word "good"
وهو بكل بساطة أن تبدؤو باستخدام كلمة "خَيّر"
in this context.
في هذا السياق.
When you think about your own country,
عندما تقوم بالتفكير في دولتك،
when you think about other people's countries,
وعندما تقوم بالتفكير بدول الآخرين
when you think about companies,
وعندما تفكر في الشركات
when you talk about the world that we live in today,
وعندما تتحدث عن العالم الذي نعيش فيه اليوم،
start using that word
استخدم هذه الكلمة
in the way that I've talked about this evening.
بالمفهوم الذي تحدثنا عنه هذا المساء.
Not good, the opposite of bad,
لا الخيّر عكس السيء،
because that's an argument that never finishes.
لأن تلك مسألة لا تنتهي أبدًا.
Good, the opposite of selfish,
الخيّر عكس الأناني،
good being a country that thinks about all of us.
والدولة الخيّرة تفكر فينا جميعا.
That's what I would like you to do,
هذا ما أود أن تفعله،
and I'd like you to use it as a stick
وأود منك أن تستخدمها كعصى
with which to beat your politicians.
تضرب بها السياسين.
When you elect them, when you reelect them,
عندما تنتخبهم وتعيد انتخابهم،
when you vote for them, when you listen
عندما تصوت لهم، وعندما تستمع
to what they're offering you,
إلى ما يعرضونه عليك،
use that word, "good,"
استخدم تلك الكلمة، "خيّر"
and ask yourself,
واسأل نفسك،
"Is that what a good country would do?"
"هل هذا ما تقوم به الدول الخيّرة؟"
And if the answer is no, be very suspicious.
وإذا كانت الإجابة لا، كن مشكّكا.
Ask yourself, is that the behavior
اسأل نفسك هل هذه طريقة تصرف
of my country?
دولتي؟
Do I want to come from a country
هل أريد أن أنتمي إلى دولة
where the government, in my name,
حيث تقوم حكومة الدولة وبإسمي
is doing things like that?
بفعل أمور مثل تلك؟
Or do I, on the other hand,
أو هل، من جهة أخرى،
prefer the idea of walking around the world
أفضل أن أمشي حول العالم
with my head held high thinking, "Yeah,
ورأسي مرفوع عاليًا مفكرا "نعم،
I'm proud to come from a good country"?
أنا فخور بأني من بلد خيّرة"؟
And everybody will welcome you.
والجميع سيرحب بك.
And everybody in the last 15 seconds
والجميع في آخر 15 ثانية
before they drift off to sleep at night will say,
قبل أن يناموا سيقولون،
"Gosh, I'm glad that person's country exists."
"يا الهي، كم أنا سعيد بوجود بلد ذلك الشخص"
Ultimately, that, I think,
في النهاية، ذلك، كما أعتقد،
is what will make the change.
هو ما سيحدث الفرق.
That word, "good,"
تلك الكلمة "خيّرة"
and the number 6.8
والرقم 6.8
and the discovery that's behind it
والاكتشاف وراءه
have changed my life.
غيّر حياتي.
I think they can change your life,
وأعتقد أنه سيغير حياتك أيضًا،
and I think we can use it to change
وأعتقد أنه يمكننا استخدام ذلك لتغيير
the way that our politicians and our companies behave,
طريقة تصرف السياسيين والشركات،
and in doing so, we can change the world.
وعندما نقوم بذلك، نستطيع أن نغير العالم.
I've started thinking very differently about
لقد بدأت طريقتي بالتفكير تتغير
my own country since I've been thinking about these things.
حول دولتي، منذ أن بدأت بالتفكير في هذه الأمور.
I used to think that I wanted to live in a rich country,
لقد كنت أفكر أني أريد أن أعيش في دولة ثرية،
and then I started thinking I wanted to live in a happy country,
وحينها فكرت بأني أريد العيش في دولة سعيدة،
but I began to realize, it's not enough.
ولكن عندها بدأت أدرك أن ذلك غير كاف.
I don't want to live in a rich country.
لا أريد العيش في دولة ثرية.
I don't want to live in a fast-growing
ولا أريد العيش بدولة سريعة النمو
or competitive country.
أو دولة تنافسية.
I want to live in a good country,
أريد أن أعيش في دولة خَيّرة،
and I so, so hope that you do too.
وأتمنى أنكم تريدون ذلك أيضًا.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)